Guide to the Washington Irving Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Washington Irving collection
1802-1966
YCAL MSS 769
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
9.8
(25 boxes)
The collection provides evidence of the personal and professional life of Washington Irving and dates from 1802 to 1966. The collection documents Irving's writing career, diplomatic work, and travels through Europe, and consists of correspondence, writings, personal papers, and printed material. Correspondents include: Thomas Aspinwall, Dmitrii Ivanovich Dolgorukii, Catherine Rodgers Irving Paris, Sarah Sanders Paris Storrow, and Moses Thomas. The collection includes journals belonging to Emily Foster with whom Irving was acquainted while living in Dresden. Documents relating to Irving's brothers can also be found in the collection; these include a manuscript notebook of John Treat Irving's "Simon Pure Papers" and Peter Irving's journals describing his travels in Europe. The collection contains an mezzotint portrait of Irving and engraved illustrations for his publications.
Irving, Washington, 1783-1859
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from various sources. For more information see catalog cards filed in the collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Washington Irving (1783-1859)
Washington Irving was an American author and statesman best known for his satirical History of New York from the Beginning of the World to the End of the Dutch Dynasty (1809) and short stories "Rip Van Winkle" and "The Legend of Sleepy Hollow" published in The Sketch Book of Geoffrey Crayon, Gent. (1819–1820). Irving also served as Secretary to the American Legation in England from 1829 to 1832 and as Minister to Spain from 1842 to 1846.
Scope and Contents
The collection provides evidence of the personal and professional life of Washington Irving and dates from 1802 to 1966. The collection documents Irving's writing career, diplomatic work, and travels through Europe, and consists of correspondence, writings, personal papers, and printed material.
Irving's creative process can be traced in notebooks and handwritten drafts. The collection includes notes and an autograph manuscript for volumes four and five of Irving's final book Life of George Washington. The various manuscript fragments contained in the collection also illustrate the American public's fascination with Irving and the culture of collecting souvenirs related to his life and writings. For this reason the majority of Irving's drafts are incomplete; for example, the library acquired two leaves from The Life and Voyages of Christopher Columbus at separate times and which are from different sections of the original manuscript. A small amount of correspondence with publishers and authors, including Charles Dickens and Sir Walter Scott, also reflect Irving's literary life. Irving's letter to William C. Preston expresses his views regarding the copyright of his works within an international context.
A few documents relating to Irving's work as a diplomat in England and Spain are also part of the collection. These include a passport with Irving's signature in his role as Secretary to the American Legation in London. Irving's correspondence with diplomat Prince Dmitrii Ivanovich Dolgorukii and Scottish painter Sir David Wilkie reflect his experience in Spain. Notably, correspondence with Prince Dmitrii Ivanovich Dolgorukii also includes Dolgorouki's correspondence from Sir David Wilkie, in which Wilkie discusses his painting and work for King George IV of England.
Irving's personal life can be traced in his correspondence with his siblings and their children (particularly his sister Catherine Rodgers Irving Paris and her daughter Sarah Sanders Paris Storrow). The collection also includes journals belonging to Emily Foster to whom Irving is believed to have proposed marriage. Documents relating to Irving's brothers -- namely John Treat and Peter -- are also included in the collection. The collection contains John Treat Irving's "Simon Pure Papers" (for which Washington Irving drew illustrations) and Peter Irving's journals describing his travels in Europe.
Stanley T.Williams's The Life of Washington Irving and extra-illustrated publications of Irving's writings attest to his reputation and lasting influence.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1804-1885. II. Writings, 1802-1972. III. Other Papers, 1807-1831. IV. Printed Material, 1850-1882.
American literature -- 19th century; Authors, American -- 19th century -- Archives; Authors, American -- New York (State); Authors and publishers; Novelists, American; Travelers' writings, American; Diaries; Engravings (prints); Authors; Aspinwall, Thomas, 1786-1876; Dolgorukiĭ, D. I., kni︠a︡zʹ (Dmitriĭ Ivanovich), -1867; Foster, Emily, 1804?-1885; Irving, John Treat, 1812-1906; Irving, Peter, 1772-1838; Irving, Washington, 1783-1859; Paris, Catherine Rodgers Irving; Storrow, Sarah Sanders Paris; Thomas, Moses, 1787-1865; Wilkie, David, Sir, 1785-1841
- Correspondence, 1804-1885; Series I; 1.46; (4 boxes)
  Arrangement
  The series is organized into three subseries: Incoming Correspondence; Outgoing Correspondence; and Third Party Correspondence.
  Scope and Contents
  The series documents Irving's professional life and personal relationships. The majority of correspondence is comprised of Irving's outgoing letters, although the series does include some incoming correspondence. Letters from Charles Dickens, Nathaniel Hawthorne, and Sir Walter Scott provide some insight into Irving's literary circle. Irving's correspondence to Colonel Thomas Aspinwall (who served as his literary agent for a period) and publishers also reflect his professional life.
  The most substantial correspondence is from Irving to various family members. Irving's correspondence with his sister Catherine Rodgers Irving Paris and his niece Sarah Sanders Paris Storrow is especially sizeable and dates from 1822 to 1858.
  The series also contains third-party correspondence belonging to Irving's brother Peter and nephew Pierre. Letters from Scottish painter David Wilkie to Irving and Prince Dmitrii Ivanovich Dolgorukii are notable for documenting Wilkie's career, including his experience in Spain and his work for the British royal family.
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - Bleecker, G.W., autograph letter, signed, Yonkers, 1842 March 17 (Box 1)
    - Campbell, Thomas, 1813 December 21 (Box 1)
    - Childs & Peterson, manuscript letter, signed, Philadelphia, 1885 August 2 (Box 1)
    - Dickens, Charles, autograph letter, signed, 1842 March 21 (Box 1)
    - Gibson, Chandler, autograph letter, signed, Esperance, New York, 1842 March 15 (Box 1)
    - Hawthorne, Nathaniel, 1852 July 16 (Box 1)
    - Haydon, Benjamin Robert, 1830 August 31 (Box 1)
    - Irving, Helen, autograph letter, signed, New York, 1855 February 5 (Box 1)
    - Kemble, Gouverneur, autograph letter, signed, Paris, France, 1809 July 1 (Box 1)
    - Lanman, Charles, autograph letter, signed, Norwich, Connecticut, 1856 August 27 (Box 1)
    - McLane, Louis, autograph letter, signed, Washington, D.C., 1831 November 4 (Box 1)
    - Matthews, Arthur, autograph letter, signed, Athenaeum Club House, London, 1830 June 3 (Box 1)
    - Mathews, Charles, June 5 (Box 1)
    - Moore, Thomas, autograph letter, signed, 1824? (Box 1)
    - Paris, Catherine Rodgers Irving, 1832 April 19 (Box 1)
    - Prescott, William Hickling, copy made in the hand of Pierre M. Irving, 1839 December 24 (Box 1)
    - Rogers, Samuel, 1832 March 6 (Box 1)
    - Scott, Sir Walter, autograph letter, 1819 November 17 (Box 1)
    - Scott, Sir Walter, autograph letter, 1819 December 4 (Box 1)
    - Sotheby, William, 1830 July 6 (Box 1)
    - Wilkie, David, 1833-1835 (Box 1)
    - Willis, Nathaniel, P., 1855 January 9 (Box 1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - Aspinwall, Thomas, autograph letters, signed, 1828-1830 (Box 1)
    - Aspinwall, Thomas, autograph letters, signed, 1831 and 1837 (Box 1)
      Includes three letters removed from Knickerbocker's History of New York, The Letters of Jonathan Oldstyle, Gent, and Tales of the Alhambra.
    - Aspinwall, Thomas, autograph letter, signed, 1835 March 8 (Box 1)
    - Aspinwall, Thomas, autograph letter, signed, 1835 April 23 (Box 1)
    - Bellows, Mr., autograph note written by third party, no year March 27 (Box 1)
    - Blackford, William M., autograph letter, signed, New York. with engraved portrait of Irving and Andrew Jackson and typed commentary on the letter, 1833 October 27 (Box 1)
    - Boteler, Alexander R., autograph letter, signed, 1853 November 11 (Box 1)
    - Brevoort, Henry, manuscript copies in the handwriting of Pierre Irving, 1810-1815 (Box 1)
    - Brevoort, Henry, autograph letter, signed, Prague, 1823 June 6 (Box 1)
    - Bryant, William Cullen, to Irving, 1832 April 24 (Box 1)
    - Buchanan, James, Secretary of State, first draft of letter, London, 1846 August 15 (Box 1)
    - Camberling, C. C., autograph letter, signed, London, 1830 August 30 (Box 1)
    - Canale, George D., autograph letter, signed, 1859 April 19 (Box 1)
    - Cardell, William S., autograph letter, signed, London, 1820 August 14 (Box 1)
    - Carey & Lea, autograph letter, signed, 1832 June 2 (Box 1)
    - Childs and Peterson, autograph letter, signed, Sunnyside, 1857 April 9 (Box 1)
    - Clarke, Mr., autograph letter, signed, no year June 5 (Box 1)
    - Clayton, John Middleton, Secretary of State and John Howard Payne, leaf from Irving's letterbook, 1849 (Box 1)
    - Colden, Cadwaller D., autograph letter, signed, Bordeaux, 1804 July 5 (Box 1)
    - Committee of the Christomathian Society of Cincinnati, autograph letter, signed, Tarrytown, 1836 October 26 (Box 1)
    - Davis, Charles A., autograph letter, signed, Sunnyside, 1859 April 4 (Box 1)
    - Dolgorukii, D. I. (Dmitrii Ivanovich), eighteen autograph letters, signed, Madrid, Seville, Alhambra, bound in full green leather, lettered in gold on front cover, 1828 January 22-1842 October 18 (Box 1)
      Includes five letters from Sir David Wilkie to Dolgorouki, April 15, 1828-November 21, 1836.
    - Duane, William, autograph letter, signed, Sunnyside, 1856 June 3 (Box 1)
    - Fairlie, Mary, autograph letters, signed, 1807 (Box 1)
    - Furman, John, manuscript copies in the handwriting of Pierre Irving, 1802-1804 (Box 1)
    - Gill, Bennington, autograph note, signed, Greenburgh, 1840 January 7 (Box 1)
    - Goforth, John, envelope, April 24 (Box 1)
    - Grinnell, Julia Irving, and Moses Hicks, four autograph letters, signed, Madrid, 1842-1844 (Box 1)
      Bound in blue full morocco with gold lettering on front cover and spine: "Washington Irving Letters from Madrid."
    - Hall, John E., autograph letter, signed, 1807 May 13 (Box 2)
    - Hicks, Elias and Alexander Beebee, manuscript copy in the handwriting of Pierre Irving, 1804 (Box 2)
    - Hicks, Elias, autograph letters, signed, Bordeaux, 1804-1805 (Box 2)
    - Irving, Helen, autograph letter, signed, 1853 June 15 (Box 2)
    - Irving, Sarah Sanders, autograph letter, signed, Birmingham, England, 1816 August 31 (Box 2)
    - Irving, William (brother), autograph letters, signed, 1804 June 26-1805 January 25 (Box 2)
    - Irving, William (nephew), autograph letter, signed, New York City, 1834 August 4 (Box 2)
    - Jackson, President Andrew, autograph note, signed, New York, 1830 October 10 (Box 2)
    - Jones, Alfred, autograph letter, signed, 1857 May 10 (Box 2)
    - Lea and Blanchard, autograph letter, signed, New York City, 1839 February 13 (Box 2)
    - Lestel, J. W., autograph letter, signed, Sunnyside, 1855 October 29 (Box 2)
    - Lossing, Benson J., autograph letter, signed, 1858 April 16 (Box 2)
    - Macon, George, autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 2)
    - Mason, John G., Secretary of the Navy, first draft of letter, Sunnyside, 1847 February 4 (Box 2)
    - Merwin, Jesse, facsimile of autograph letter, signed, Sunnyside, 1851 February 12 (Box 2)
    - Moore, T. W. C., autograph letter, signed, Madrid, 1843 January 10 (Box 2)
    - Morris, General George P., autograph letters, signed, 1853 (Box 2)
    - Murray, John, to Irving, 1832 January 30 (Box 2)
    - Nevins, Russell H., autograph note, signed, New York City, 1839 February 13 (Box 2)
    - Paris, Catherine Rodgers Irving, autograph letters, signed, 1822-1836; 11 (Box 2)
    - Paris, Catherine Rodgers Irving and Sarah Sanders Paris Storrow, autograph letters, signed, 1842-1843; 69 (Box 2)
    - Paris, Catherine Rodgers Irving, manuscript copies in unidentified handwriting, 1842-1843 (Box 2)
    - Paris, Catherine Rodgers Irving and Sarah Sanders Paris Storrow, autograph letters, signed, 1844-1858; 118 (Box 3)
    - Paris, Catherine Rodgers Irving and Sarah Sanders Paris Storrow, empty envelopes, 1836-1845 (Box 3)
    - Preston, William C., autograph letter, signed, regarding copyright law, 1837 February 22 (Box 4)
    - Ramsay, Thomas, autograph note, signed, Sunnyside, June 7 (Box 4)
    - Silliman, Benjamin, autograph letters, signed, Sunnyside, 1853-1856 (Box 4)
    - Storrow, Sarah Sanders Paris, autograph letters, signed, 1836-1841; 17 (Box 4)
      Related Archival Materials note
      Paris, Catherine Rodgers Irving and Sarah Sanders Paris Storrow, autograph letters, signed
    - Storrow, Sarah Sanders Paris, autograph note, signed, Birmingham, 1842 May 20 (Box 4)
    - Storrow, Sarah Sanders Paris, autograph letter, signed, Madrid, 1845 February 5 (Box 4)
    - Taylor, Bayard, autograph note, signed, Sunnyside, 1854 October (Box 4)
    - Thomas, Moses, bookseller, six autograph letters, signed, Liverpool, 1815-1816; 2 (Box 4)
    - Tiffany, Osmond, autograph letter, signed, 1858 December 22 (Box 4)
    - Waldo, Samuel L., autograph note, signed, Sunnyside, 1858 February 5 (Box 4)
    - Watson, Elkanah, autograph letter, signed, Greenburgh, 1837 July 8 (Box 4)
    - Watson, Dr., autograph letter, signed, 1842 April 6 (Box 4)
    - Wayne, James M., autograph letter, signed, New York City, 1833 December 25 (Box 4)
    - Webster, Daniel, autograph letter, signed, 1851 December 13 (Box 4)
    - Wilkie, David, autograph letters, signed and essay, autograph manuscript, on Sir David Wilkie in Spain, 1828 and 1836 (Box 4)
    - Unidentified, autograph letter, signed, 1811 December 11 (Box 4)
  - Third Party Correspondence
    - Irving, Peter, autograph letter, signed to Colonel Thomas Aspinwall, 1829 (Box 4)
    - Irving, Peter, autograph letter, signed to Colonel Richard Dodge, 1807 (Box 4)
    - Irving, Pierre, to Henry M. Morfit, autograph letter, signed, 1844 August 10 (Box 4)
    - Irving, Pierre, letters to him and papers connected with him, 1859-1864 (Box 4)
      Includes letters from Charles Loring Elliott (October 31, 1864), Henry Wadsworth Longfellow (December 16, 1859), William J. Paulding (April 3, 1860) and a certificate of copyright for volume I of his Life and Letters of Washington Irving (May 3, 1862) and manuscript note by Hiram Paulding about John Paulding. Also includes photograph of Pierre Irving.
- Writings, 1802-1972; Series II; 7.09; (17 boxes)
  The series is organized into two subseries: Writings by Irving and Writings of Others.
  The series is comprised of various manuscripts written by Irving throughout his literary career from early works to his final book project Life of George Washington. Following Irving's death many of his manuscripts were separated and distributed as gifts to friends or sold to autograph collectors; for this reason many of the drafts are incomplete and consist of a few chapters or single pages.
  The subseries Writings of Others contains the "Simon Pure Papers" by Irving's brother and for which Irving created a few illustrations. Also included is academic scholarship on Irving, namely Stanley T. Williams's biography The Life of Washington Irving.
  - Writings by Irving
    - "Anecdotas," autograph manuscript of two short stories, undated (Box 5)
    - Bracebridge Hall, autograph manuscript, 1 page, before 1822 (Box 5)
    - "The Count Van Horn," Wolfert's Roost and Other Papers, autograph manuscript leaf, before 1855 (Box 5)
    - "French Romance," autograph manuscript, and excerpts from Irving's diary, written in Paris, 1821 April 25-26, undated (Box 5)
    - History of New York
      - Manuscript notebook with original drafts of passages used in volume two of the New York, 1809, edition, undated (Box 5)
      - Indictment of Colonel Butler by General Wilkinson, 1803 (Box 5)
        Document confirming veracity of Washington Irving's account of the incident in A History of New York.
    - Life of George Washington
      - Autograph manuscript notes, bound in red full morocco with gold tooled spine and edges, undated (Box 5)
      - Autograph manuscript, volume IV-V, with chapter outline in handwriting of Pierre Munro Irving, 1889, undated (Box 5)
        Includes letter to Mrs. Charles L. McAlpine from George Irving (1889) gifting manuscript to Mrs. McAlpine.
        Bound in tan full crushed levant morocco.
      - Autograph manuscript fragment, 1868, 1966, undated (Box 5)
        Includes correspondence from Henry T. Drowne to Caleb F. Harris (November 6 and December 16, 1868). Drowne gifted the manuscript fragment to Harris and explains the manuscript's provenance in one of his letters. Also includes letter to the Beinecke Library from Charlie Williamson, who gifted the manuscript fragment and letters to the library.
    - The Life and Voyages of Christopher Columbus
      - Autograph manuscript leaf, before 1828 (Box 5)
      - Autograph manuscript, fragment from upper half of single page numbered 526, undated (Box 5)
    - Notes on abbés, autograph manuscript, published in "Editor's Table" in the Knickerbocker Magazine, April 1840, before 1840 (Box 5)
    - My Uncle, autograph manuscript, undated, 1964 (Box 5)
      Includes article about the manuscript for the Yale University Library Gazette (January 1964) by Barbara D. Simison.
    - Pelayo and the Merchant's Daughter, draft, corrected, and printed version, before 1840 (Box 5)
    - The Sketch Book of Geoffrey Crayon, Gent., "Notes while preparing Sketch Book, etc.," notebook written in pencil and ink and photostat copies, 1817; 2 (Box 6)
    - "Story Told by Peter the Venerable Abbot of Cluni," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 6)
    - "Summary: The Amistad," notes, autograph manuscript, 1842 June (Box 6)
    - "Torre de la Observacion," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 6)
    - "Village of Las Dos Hermanas," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 6)
    - Manuscript notes written in Madrid, dealing with Irving's personal reminiscences (chiefly of his experiences while living in England), 1843 January 10-24 (Box 6)
      Includes transcript and article for the Yale University Library Gazette (January 1963) by Barbara Simison.
    - "Notes concerning the United States 1818," notebook containing Irving's handwritten extracts from travel books, 1817 December (Box 6)
    - Notebook with entries both in ink and in pencil, occasional drawings, bound in calfskin, contains descriptive passages, poetry, discussion of English literature, and other observations, 1810; 2 (Box 7)
      Includes photostat copies
    - Notebook containing memoranda regarding Irving's visit to Alhambra, Spain, and Bordeaux, France, 1829 March 29-July 11, 1960s; 2 (Box 7)
      Includes photostat copies and transcription
    - Notebook containing memoranda regarding Irving's visit to Alhambra, Spain, and Bordeaux, France, additional copies, 1960s (Box 8)
    - "Notes of a Tour in Europe in 1804-5 Vol. 2d. From January 24th to April 13th 1805 Containing Route from Messina To Sicily and To Rome with Residence at Different Places," notebook, 1804-1805 (Box 8)
    - Notes, written after 1850, in answer to twelve questions dealing with the times and places of writing; the dates of various editions with amounts received for each; and the dates of revision of the following: Tales of a Traveller, Companions of Columbus, Tour on the Prairies, and Abbotsford (Box 8)
    - Private memoranda, manuscript fragment of autobiography, undated (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous manuscript pages, notes for books, passages of description, and pieces of letters, undated (Box 8)
    - Photocopies of manuscripts offered for sale to Beinecke Library by Kenneth W. Rendell Inc., 1972 (Box 8)
  - Writings by Others
    - Irving, John Treat, "Simon Pure Papers," notebook containing fair copies of sermons, poetry, and a play, written under the pseudonym "Simon Pure", 1802 (Box 8)
    - Original pen-and-ink and pencil sketches, drawn by Washington Irving, likely as illustrations for his brother's "Simon Pure Papers.", undated, 1891 (Box 8)
      Includes letter from John Treat Irving explaining origin of the "Simon Pure Papers" and authenticating the drawings by Washington Irving.
    - "Philip V. of Spain," manuscript in unidentified hand, undated (Box 8)
    - Williams, Stanley T., The Life of Washington Irving
      - Draft, typescript, corrected, before 1935; 31 (Box 9)
      - Draft, typescript, corrected, and notes, before 1935; 9 (Box 10)
      - Research notes and correspondence, before 1935; 14 (Box 11)
      - Research notes and correspondence, before 1935; 8 (Box 12)
      - Research notes and correspondence, before 1935; 9 (Box 13)
      - Research notes and correspondence, before 1935; 7 (Box 14)
      - Research notes and correspondence, before 1935; 12 (Box 15)
      - Research notes and correspondence, before 1935; 12 (Box 16)
      - Research notes and correspondence, before 1935; 9 (Box 17)
      - Photostats of letters and journals, before 1935; 6 (Box 18)
      - Transcriptions of letters and journals, before 1935; 4 (Box 19)
      - Transcriptions of state department documents, before 1935; 5 (Box 20)
      - Photostats of notebooks and journals, before 1935; 13 (Box 21)
- Other Papers, 1807-1831; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  The Other Papers series contains notes made by Irving in both English and Spanish. The journals of Peter Irving record the travels of Washington Irving's brother through Europe in 1807. The journals of Emily Foster, dating from roughly 1820 to 1830, can also be found in Other Papers, and are notable for containing observations by Foster with whom Irving was acquainted while living in Dresden. The journals were published in 1938 by Stanley T. Williams and Leonard B. Beach.
  - Terms of Settlement for the Conquest of Grenada, autograph manuscript, 1829 January 10 (Box 22)
  - Metode que se debe guardar para conservar la memoria del origen de las Casas, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 22)
  - Certificacion de Armas, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 22)
  - Estimated cost of constructing a wooden crib, written in unidentified hand, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 22)
  - Irving, Peter
    - Journal, Nice, Genoa, Florence, and Rome, 1807 April-May (Box 22)
    - Journal, Bologna, Ferrar, Padua, Venice, Milan, and Alps, 1807 June (Box 22)
    - Journal, Geneva -- Glaciers -- Lucerne & Lakes, 1807 June 21-July 5 (Box 22)
    - Journal, England and Scotland, 1807 August-September (Box 22)
    - Miscellaneous bills and cards laid in, undated (Box 22)
  - Foster, Emily, manuscript journal and common place books, two volumes, in her handwriting, with her signature inside the front cover of each, 1820-1830 (Box 22)
  - Passports belonging to Henry Brooks, London, one of which includes Washington Irving's signature while serving as Secretary to the American Legation in England, 1830-1831 (Box 22)
- Printed Material, 1850-1882; Series IV; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  The Printed Material series contains extra-illustrated books and a number of printed items. Also included is a photograph of an unidentified home and photographs and engravings of Spain.